Guide to the Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC) records, 1954-1990 and undated UA.26.03.0007
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC) records
1954-1990 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Triangle Universities Computation Center
UA.26.03.0007
18.2 Linear Feet
The Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC) was incorporated in 1965 as a cooperative venture between Duke University, North Carolina State University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, with the goal of providing main-frame computing services, such as electronic data and batch processing, to the universities, RTI International and others. It dissolved in 1990 due to financial difficulties, the increased use of personal computers, and disagreements among the partners. Materials in the collection include administrative records, correspondence, meeting minutes, financial and statistical reports, memoranda, proposals, newsletters, photographs, slides, a scrapbook, and other materials from the Triangle Universities Computation Center.
11,400 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for use by researchers. In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use excluding scrapbook and photographs which are located at the repository.
Provenance
The Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC) records were received by the University Archives as a series of transfers from 1974-2000.
Historical Note
The Triangle Universities Computation Center (TUCC) was incorporated in 1965 as a cooperative venture between Duke University, North Carolina State University and the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill. Owned by all three universities, its primary goals were to provide each institution with adequate computing facilities as economically as possible, minimizing the number of system programming personnel and fostering greater cooperation between the universities with an exchange of system programs and ideas. Housed in the Science and Technology Research Center in centrally located Research Triangle Park (RTP), North Carolina, TUCC eventually expanded its main-frame computer services beyond the three universities, to support the electronic data processing needs of RTI International and other research organization located in RTP.
TUCC's decline began in the mid-1980s with an unsuccessful bid to purchase and operate a supercomputer in RTP, with the goal of transforming RTP into a "Southern Silicon Valley". This failed bid, coupled with increasing financial difficulties, the growing number of clients purchasing their own personal computers and thus needing fewer TUCC services, and escalating disagreements among member institutions about how the center should be run, ultimately lead to the dissolution of TUCC in September, 1990.
Collection Overview
The TUCC records spans the years 1954-1990. The collection is arranged into two series: Administrative Records, 1954-1990 and Visual Materials, 1966-1989 and undated.
Materials in the collection include administrative records, correspondence, meeting minutes, financial and statistical reports, memoranda, proposals, newsletters, photographs, slides, a scrapbook, and other materials from the Triangle Universities Computation Center.
Related Material
Inventory of the Business and Finance Division records, 1956-1983.
University Archives, Duke University.
Inventory of the Department of Computer Science records, 1961-1978.
University Archives, Duke University.
Preliminary Inventory of the Thomas M. Gallie Papers, 1955 – 1972.
University Archives, Duke University.
Preliminary Inventory of the Vice President for Business and Finance records, 1962-1985.
University Archives, Duke University.
TUCC Information services; Triangle Universities Computation Center -- Programming services; Universities and colleges -- North Carolina; Electronic data processing -- United States -- History; Information technology -- North Carolina; Electronic data processing -- Batch processing; Electronic data processing -- Distributed processing; Education -- Data processing; Education -- Data processing -- Planning; Triangle Universities Computation Center; Triangle Universities Computation Center; University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill; North Carolina State University; Duke University
- Administrative Records, 1954-1990, 10 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  These files consist of a variety of administrative materials, including reports, financial statements, correspondence, meeting minutes, grant proposals, and news articles documenting the history of TUCC. These materials detail the creation and initial funding of TUCC, its activities over the course of its operations, and its eventual dissolution in September, 1990.
  - Anniversary Celebration (10th & 20th) Information, 1975, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1970/71-1973/74 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1974/75-1977/78 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1987/79-1981/82 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1982/83-1986/87 (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation & Bylaws, 1965-1989 (Box 1)
  - Assistant Directors' Meeting Minutes, 1972-1980 (Box 1)
  - Assistant Directors' Meeting Minutes, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
  - Assistant Directors' Meeting Minutes, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Correspondence, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Correspondence, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Correspondence, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1971 Jan-Jun (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1971 Jul-Dec (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1972 Jan-Jun (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1972 Jul-Dec (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1973 Jan-Jul (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1973 Aug-Dec (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1974 Jan-Jun (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1974 Jul-Dec (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1978 Jan-Sep (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1978 Oct-Dec (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1980 Jan-Jun (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1980 Jul-Dec (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1981 Jan-Jun (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1981 Jul-Dec (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1982 Jan-Jun (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1982 Jul-Dec (Box 2)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1983 Jan-Jun (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1983 Jul-Dec (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1985 Jan-Jun (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1985 Jul-Dec (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1986 Jan-Jun (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1986 Jul-Dec (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1988 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1989 Jan-Jun (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1989 Jul-Dec (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors Minutes, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Campus Center Directors (CCD) Meeting Minutes, 1973-1976 (Box 3)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1977 (Box 3)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1978 (Box 3)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1979 (Box 3)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1980 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1981 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1982 Jan-Jun (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1982 Jul-Dec (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1983 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1984 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1986 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1987 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1988 (Box 4)
  - CCD Meeting Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Campus Systems Programmers Meeting Minutes, 1970-1974 (Box 4)
  - Campus Systems Programmers (CSP) Meeting Minutes, 1975-1980 (Box 4)
  - CSP Meeting Minutes, 1981-1985 (Box 4)
  - CSP Meeting Minutes, 1986-1989 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Long Range Planning Minutes, 1966 (Box 4)
  - Communications, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Computation Center Director's Meeting Minutes, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
  - Computation Center Director's Meeting Minutes, 1972 (Box 5)
  - Computation Center Director's Meeting Minutes, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Computation Center Director's Meeting Minutes, 1974 Jan-Jul (Box 5)
  - Computation Center Director's Meeting Minutes, 1974 Sep-1975 Dec (Box 5)
  - Computation Center Director's Meeting Minutes, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Computer Planning Committee Minutes and Correspondence, 1967 Jan-Aug (Box 5)
  - Computer Planning Committee Minutes and Correspondence, 1967 Sep-Dec (Box 5)
  - Computer Planning Committee Minutes and Correspondence, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Computer Planning Committee Minutes and Correspondence, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 5)
  - Document Demand, 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - DoD Auditors, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Duke Data Channel Newsletter, 1988 May-Nov (Box 5)
  - Equipment Purchase, 1969 (Box 5)
  - FE Status Meeting, 1982-1984 (Box 5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1977 (Box 5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1981 (Box 6)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1982-1985 (Box 6)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1987 (Box 6)
  - Finance Committee Minutes, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Finances, 1968-1970 (Box 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1966-1969 (Box 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1970-1972 (Box 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1973-1976 (Box 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1977-1981 (Box 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1982-1987 (Box 6)
  - Financial Statements, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
  - Historical Information on TUCC, 1965-1975 and undated (Box 6)
  - History of TUCC, 1966-1985 (Box 6)
  - History RTC, 1964-1967 (Box 6)
  - IBM Correspondence, 1954-1969 (Box 6)
  - Installation Management Documents (IM002 - IM035, including Index), 1975-1987 (Box 7)
  - Internal Documents (IA001-IA047), 1984-1987 (Box 7)
  - Internal Documents (IM37-IM112), 1975-1988 (Box 7)
  - Long Range Technical Planning Committee Minutes, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (AC-01 through AC-37), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (AD-01 through AD-23), 1965-1966 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (GI-01 through GI-26), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (IA-01 through IA-14), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (IP-01 through IP-09), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (IS-06 through IS-51), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (LS-01 through LS-27), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (NL-01), 1966 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (OP-01 through OP-44), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (PAD-01 through PAD-23), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (TAD-01 through TAD-05), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (TP-01 through TP-19), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum (WP-01 through WP-20), 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum - Administrative, 1968-1970 (Box 7)
  - Memorandum - Indexes and General, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - News Articles About TUCC, 1967-1975 (Box 7)
  - News Released From TUCC, 1966-1988 (Box 7)
  - Newspaper Articles - Supercomputer & TUCC's Demise, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - North Carolina Computer Orientation Project (NCCOP) Memorandum, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
  - North Carolina State University (NCSU) Computing Center Newsletter, 1988-1989 (Box 7)
  - Planning and Evaluation Committee Minutes, 1966-1968 (Box 7)
  - President's Correspondence, 1983 Jan-Jun (Box 7)
  - President's Correspondence, 1983 Jul-Dec (Box 7)
  - President's Correspondence, 1984 Jan-Jun (Box 8)
  - President's Correspondence, 1984 Jul-Dec (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1981 Jan-Jun (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1981 Jun-Dec (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1982 (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1985 Jan-Jun (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1985 Jun-Dec (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1986 Jan-Jun (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1986 Jun-Dec (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1987 Jan-Jun (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1988 Jan-Jun (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1988 Jun-Dec (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1989 Jan-Jun (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1989 Jun-Dec (Box 8)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1990 Jan-Oct (Box 8)
  - Purchase of TUCC Computer Correspondence, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Proposals - IBM, 1965-1967 (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [Duke's proposal for the Modernization of the Computer Facilities], 1965 Feb (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [UNC's proposal for the Modernization of the Computer Facilities plus Amendment], 1965 Feb (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [Duke & NCSU proposal for the Establishment of TUCC], 1965 Jul (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [Duke's proposal for the Expansion of Computation Capacity], 1968 Sep (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [NCSU's proposal for the Expansion of Computation Capacity], 1968 Sep (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [UNC's proposal for the Expansion of Computation Capacity], 1968 Sep (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [Duke's proposal for a Computer Science Laboratory], 1968 Sep (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [Support of NCCOP], 1970 Apr (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF [For Triangle Supercomputer Center], 1983 Dec-1984 May (Box 9)
  - Proposals - NSF For Arpanet Access], 1985 Aug (Box 9)
  - Proposals to TUCC - Control Data Corporation, 1965 Mar (Box 9)
  - Proposals to TUCC - General Electric, 1965 (Box 9)
  - Proposals to TUCC - IBM, 1965 Mar (Box 9)
  - President and Director's Correspondence, 1990 Jan-Oct (Box 9)
  - Proposals to TUCC - Univac, 1965 Mar (Box 9)
  - Rate Setting, 1965-1971 and undated (Box 10)
  - Reports, 1966-1969 (Box 10)
  - Supernews (TUCC newsletter), 1984-1986 (Box 10)
  - System Programmers Meeting Minutes, 1971-1977 (Box 10)
  - Tax Exempt Status Correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 10)
  - Tax Exempt Status Correspondence, 1971-1975 (Box 10)
  - TUCC Newsline, 1969-1973 (Box 10)
  - TUCC Output Newsletter, 1983-1988 (Box 10)
  - University Computing Center Committee Minutes, 1969-1971 (Box 10)
  - UNC Newsbrief, 1988 May-1989 May (Box 10)
  - Utilization Reports, 1968-1970 (Box 10)
  - Williams, Leland H., 1961, 1985 (Box 10)
  - Wylbur Subcommittee Meeting Minutes, 1981-1983 (Box 10)
- Visual Materials, 1968-1991 and undated, 4 boxes
  Materials in the collection include photographs (both black and white and color), color slides, microfilm reels, a scrapbook and videotape documenting social functions and operational activities related to the Triangle Universities Computation Center. Of particular interest are the microfilm reels copied by Control Data Corporation (CDC) at TUCC as part of their discovery procedure relative to the anti-trust suit against IBM. Due to the fragile nature of the materials, items in Box 11 are located in off-site storage.
  - Microfilm Reels, 1972 (Box 11)
  - Photograph Negatives, 1975 and undated (Box 11)
  - Videotape - Dr. Williams lecture, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Scrapbook, 1965-1990 (Box 12)
  - TUCC Photographs, 1966, 1971, 1973-1975 (Box 13)
  - TUCC Photographs, 1975-1976, 1979 (Box 13)
  - TUCC Photographs, 1981, 1982-1983, 1986, 1989 (Box 13)
  - TUCC Photographs (Miscellaneous company events), undated (Box 13)
  - TUCC Photographs (Operations/Employees), undated (Box 13)
  - TUCC Photographs (Picnics), undated (Box 13)
  - TUCC Slides, 1965-1967 (Box 14)
  - TUCC Slides (Duke), 1968 (Box 14)
  - TUCC Slides (NCSU, UNC), 1968 (Box 14)
  - TUCC Slides, 1971 (Box 14)
  - TUCC Slides, 1979 (Box 14)
  - TUCC Slides, 1982 (Box 14)
  - TUCC Slides, undated (Box 14)